so here's what I want to do I want to
level set what is a staff engineer right
so this is a a chart that I stole from
staff.com it's a great resource if you
all want to check it out I have no
affiliation with them but generally the
way these things work in the engineering
world is you have a entry level engineer
and then midlevel and then Senior and
that's where it becomes interesting you
can either go down the IC ladder which
is a yellow box or you can become a
manager but at at a lot of companies
senior is like a terminal level and
that's where you have options and that's
why it's important to like get to that
point and then you can decide okay do I
want to go down the IC ladder or
management we're talking about the
decision here if you want to pursue
going down that individual contributor
ladder and staff engineer is
particularly interesting because that's
where I consider you're the first true
level where you have to be a leader you
have to even if you're not a manager
you're a leader as a individual engineer
and not everyone gets the staff engineer
it is a very challenging promotion it's
also worth calling out that it's Unique
in the engineering world that you have a
viable path to getting paid more and
having more influence and more scope as
an individual not as a manager if you
think about a salesperson for example or
maybe even like a product manager it's
very challenging but I don't think
there's such a thing as like a
distinguished salesperson like the way
you acrew more compensation and more
scope as a salesperson is you go and
manage more sales people but engineering
is unique in that we have leverage we
have tools at our dispos osal that allow
us to make ourselves or other people
more productive and that's a pretty
magical thing I think about our role as
an engineer and I think it's worth just
reflecting on that and we'll probably
talk about that today just one other
thing I want to talk about here is like
one way to think about the progression
is what is your scope as you progress
the ladder right so entry level you're
talking about a task and then a feature
and a project and when you get to staff
you're talking about multiple projects
or maybe even a whole product right so
you really are talking about many people
being impacted many different parts of
the code base and then you go all the
way up to principle or distinguished and
then you have perhaps impact across the
whole industry like you've invented some
open source framework or some way of
doing like a methodology that is adopted
across the whole company or industry
okay so I'll pause there and now let's
go into open Q&A I have a couple
prepared and maybe the one that I would
like to start with is that a big part of
being a staff engineer is getting enough
scope to justify the promotion and not
all problems that you can tackle are
created equal and so I'm curious for
each of you how did you identify which
problems in your career are actually
worth solving does that make sense
because you could work on menial bug
fixes that never get you promoted how
did you all figure out what to work on
yeah I can jump in here so I when I was
at Netflix I actually was that's where I
felt like I was at that inflection point
between senior and staff and initially I
was working on like these
detection projects of trying to detect
threat actors and all this stuff with
Flink and they were trying to build out
this thing called like a sockless
security system like a it's like a
security system without a security
Operation Center and it was like all
just automated and one of the things I
recognized pretty quickly was that this
was a lot that this was a lot that this
was not this was like almost too
ambitious and so um I noticed that there
was another project that we were working
on which was like this graph database
that was going to hold on to all the
information on like applications
databases data sets customer data like
all the different connections of just
everything in the infrastructure and it
was going to be that fundamental
infrastructure and they were like hey
Zach do you want to work on this and I'm
like that sounds like something that is
g to give value even if even if it
doesn't get used for that case right it
has branching use cases and I recognized
that I needed to get off of detection
and onto that and that's really where
that's when Netflix gave me a lot more
money that's when I definitely got a lot
more respect from people at Netflix and
I definitely felt like I was in that
more leadership role after I transition
to that and I think that was the big
thing I recognized was that like more
than just like what you were saying that
rul about you don't want to be working
on like tasks or things that don't have
enough scope but you also don't want to
be working on projects that are like
high in the sky and projects that like
are risky right that might not even pan
out right because that's also very
important what I've seen the more senior
people get the more they have this
muscle to determine how much impact
there is in a project before investing
time into it and so you might experience
this where you're asking more senior
person for some small change and they
might actually never get to it because
they have that muscle and they're
checking it they might be quick to
backlog things and at the same time if
you are able to show them projects that
have particular scope maybe they involve
many different orgs or maybe the metrics
and road map Milestones that they're
achieving are quite important to the org
like maybe it's something that matters
to a group of 30 people rather than
something that's like a small thing
within a team developing that ability to
see what matters and see what is
impactful and then invest your time
accordingly is really important and how
do you develop that muscle Ryan is it
just like looking at past projects and
figure out what worked yeah I think the
way that I developed that is through
looking at the incentives of the org so
you can see most teams publish plans and
you can see some team is planning on
moving this metric by 5% or something
like that and I have an idea that's
going to move it by 7% or something in
my mind I'm thinking okay that project
if I do that that achieves A Team level
goal so it's somewhat substantial also
there's some intuition too I think at
some point I worked on some ads projects
even though it was like completely
unrelated to my team just because I saw
okay there's a pretty substantial
opportunity for revenue and I just knew
that okay this is going to be good for
the business and it turned out that it
it was quite impactful and that led to
my senior promotion so it was something
that no one really assigned to me and I
was just digging around for ways to have
impact and then one quick logistical
note so there are a bunch of questions
coming in chat so please keep those
coming for questions that you also want
answered then give a reaction to it and
that'll help the five of us prioritize
what we want to tackle I have a question
for Karly and Lee given that you both
have management experience a very
tactical one is do you like or when you
were going through the ranks to a staff
engineer how explicit were you that I
want to be a staff engineer help me
here's the timeline and like how
transparent was that conversation with
the manager and maybe
relatedly what do you look for what
advice would you share with people here
to look for in a manager who can support
them to get to this high of a level yeah
that's an interesting question so I
manage staff Engineers now as part of my
role and I will say that everyone
handles whether they feel comfortable
asking for a promotion differently a lot
of the time I'd say 50% of the time that
I've been approached about wanting a
promotion to staff level I've felt that
person wasn't ready and the other half
of the time I felt that person was ready
a long time ago and so it's really a
personality thing I think the people who
feel most comfortable asking maybe are
the ones that do a lot more
self-promotion and maybe feel like they
want to take on ambitious projects even
when they haven't shown that they're
ready and then the other group of people
are the people who feel like they have
to do a lot to prove exactly that
they're ready and maybe get one year
past being ready before they feel
comfortable asking I don't know the best
way to go about this or how you balance
either one of those things I think it's
probably healthy to do some self
reflection and see if you actually think
you're ready but also not set the bar so
high for yourself if you're a shy type
of person that you end up holding
yourself back by not asking soon enough
um and it's been funny I've very rarely
seen anyone ask for it like right when
they're ready either too early or a
little too late yeah so my take on that
and the sort of like people asking about
it or seeking it is that there there is
this difference in people who are really
ambitious and really want to move up
quickly and they might have sometimes an
inflated sense of self and like where
they're at and then the other people
that are maybe more reserved are like oh
I've been told that promotions are
trailing so even if I'm performing at
that level I shouldn't ask about it yet
because I haven't been doing it for long
enough and my take is while it's true at
a lot of big tech companies promotions
are trailing if you aren't having the
conversation then you don't know know
what you're missing and you may think
that you're knocking it out of the park
and you're just waiting for your manager
to hand you a promotion or tell you
they're putting you up and you haven't
even asked and they're like oh yeah your
Tech is solid but you haven't done
anything to improve the lives of the
engineers on the team or reached out
across teams or presented your work to
Executives like you're missing a lot
like we need to cover that and you
hadn't mentioned you wanted to be
promoted and people will of course I
want to be promoted that's not true as
having managed people not everyone wants
a promotion or wants to pursue that now
it might be that they don't want to take
that work on and they may never want to
be promoted and if they're in a terminal
role at senior why they may not want it
so you need to actually Express that you
are interested but you don't have to
express it when you're you think you're
ready you can express I am interested in
moving up the technical track I don't
want to move to management and I don't
want to stay at my current level I do
want to move up but I don't think that
I'm ready now I just want your
perspective perspective on What's
Missing and I want us to start making a
plan and working on documentation so
that when I am ready you have all the
collateral you need but you can talk
about your career in that way with your
manager it is really important that you
share that is what your interest is
because they may not know otherwise and
they may not they may be like oh yeah
they're doing a really solid job for
them to get a high rating in this role I
need them to do this work that might be
different work than I they want to take
on something that requires more leader
ership and that isn't going to check the
boxes on their current roles rubric for
them to get the very highest rating but
it may set the stage for them to get
promoted and those could be like
different so even if you're a high
performer they may not be thinking like
yeah we're going to promote you in the
next few quarters and that's a great
Point Lee about promotions being
trailing at many of these companies
there's a very related question Carly
for you you mentioned that half the
people who came for the promotion were
ready they were ready for a year they
had been ready
so Diana I think is asking would you
promote someone without asking or do you
always want to get their permission want
them to initiate what has been your
philosophy with that I think it can go
both ways I've I can think of times
where I have come to someone with a
promotion when they haven't necessarily
asked and been like I think you're ready
for this do you want this but the
majority of the time I have 44 Engineers
under me like I can't necessarily keep
track of every single person's
progression at every single point at the
year-end reviews it's a good time for me
to reflect but if you feel ready or you
feel like you're going above and beyond
in between them don't wait for me to
come to you at your yearend review right
that's the best Cadence for me because
that's when I have the most to reflect
on the past year I'm doing planning for
the next year I'm trying to see where we
want to grow our team and how we want to
grow alongside the business I think that
if you wait for that's taking kind of a
passive approach to your own career and
your own life it's better to be more
active than than not right in the same
vein it's better to ask too early than
too late for my opinion because I see
very little downside to asking too early
other than like Lee said getting
feedback on where you can grow as long
as you can take feedback right and I
think that's the big distinction if
you're going to ask for a promotion and
you're told that it's too early be
willing to hear the feedback because you
probably have blind spots that you're
not seeing your promotion doesn't come
out of my paycheck right it doesn't
really affect me necessarily if I feel
like you're ready it's in my best
interest to fight for you as your
manager there's no reason why I would
want to gate keep that from you if I'm a
good manager we've all had toxic people
in our lives so forget that those people
exist for a second and just assume that
everyone is well intentioned if your
manager says you're not ready it's not
because they're setting some sort of
unreasonable precedent or they're
wanting to be gatekeeping most likely
it's because you have a blind spot that
you're not seeing and how you handle
feedback is as much a part of whether I
think you're ready for promotion as
anything else because to me a staff
engineer needs to be able to hear
feedback from their leaders hear
feedback from their team implement it
maturely and be self-reflective and if
you take feedback and you get mad or you
argue or you say I'm actually ready
because of X Y and Z and you get
combative you're further proving the
point that you're not necessarily ready
so I'd say asking early doesn't have
many downsides sides unless you're not
someone who can handle feedback and
handle hearing the word no and I want to
put a really fine point on what Karly
just said about like your ability to
take feedback and what you do with
feedback being an indicator in and of
itself the first time my manager tried
to promote me to L6 as a manager at
Amazon it didn't go through and when he
came to me I was very tactical about it
and was like okay cool so what was
missing what were the biggest objections
how are we going to fix that going
through each thing and being like okay
what's the artifact for that you're
saying that I'm missing this how are we
going to show the next time that's not
the problem and a month later I went on
paternity leave and then when I came
back I was promoted I didn't really do
anything different except ask how to fix
it and come up with the ideas of what we
going to fill the Gap and that was
essentially like what pushed it over so
that will nness to hear the feedback and
take action on it was what got me
promoted not doing one more project or
my team doing one more project so just
she's right what I want to just add one
more thing here about this though
because if you disagree with the
feedback and you actually do think that
like it's [__] interview and see
what happens and uh maybe another
company will agree with you and that's
what's happened in my career and that's
because I've only ever been promoted one
time in my career and that was from
Junior to midlevel every other promotion
has come from a hop yeah you don't have
to freaking like if you if you have a
manager who's trying to carrot and stick
your ass like all the way up and all
that stuff freaking like maybe just
leave that's like another option that is
also an equally viable option that can
also work but you also still need to
learn how to take feedback I'm not
saying I'm not trying to be like oh yeah
don't take any feedback always just
leave I'm not that that far right but
like sometimes like there are managers
out there who do give you feedback that
are that is absolutely ridiculous that
is like not true and they actually don't
know who you are and so that's where
interviewing outside especially if
you're getting feedback that you
disagree with that is a very good thing
because then the market will tell you if
you're ready as well the market will
tell you Carly I 100% agree with you
about you should ask too early like one
thing that has become increasingly
obvious to me throughout my career is
that expression of the squeaky wheel
gets the greas if you want attention you
want money you want anything Make Some
Noise right if you want to talk about
how great your work is you want to talk
about promotion you have to advocate for
yourself and you have to talk about it I
think the Nuance here is the phrasing of
it how you frame yourself and what you
want matters a ton I think that's Lee
you were alluding to that a little bit
if you say hey I joined the company a
week ago I want to get promoted you're
not going to get very many Advocates on
your team or your manager probably won't
advocate for you but if instead you
frame it as hey I'm new my goal my
number one goal right now is I want to
ramp up I want to have a ton of impact I
want to help the people on the team but
would you be okay in three months can we
have a check-in about what promotion
looks like right if I was a manager I
would 100% say yeah I'm totally aligned
with you right now focus on ramping up
Landing some tasks writing some code and
then in three months I am more than
happy to figure out how you're trending
and what you can do to get promoted that
way you've communicated that you really
care about promotion but your priorities
are straight like your priorities are
correct at least from the team
perspective so I feel like the the way
you advocate for yourself matters a lot
definitely yeah and I would just add
asking for promotions early talking
about it explicitly I know some people
feel a little uncomfortable about doing
that or maybe like it's asking for too
much but it's just definitely better
I've experienced it at every point
before getting promoted I was very
explicit about hey I'm this level what
do I need to do to get to the next level
and it was not an uncomfortable
conversation and my manager was also
happy about it too because he wants me
to grow because then his team is having
more impact and in some cases too when
they would say oh you're probably going
to get promoted to this level I would
ask even about the next level after that
because thinking okay this one's
probably going to go through what's the
next thing I can do how can I keep going
and keep that momentum so that's even
more cringe if you don't like asking for
promos to ask for two in advance but you
totally can my manager is not upset at
all and it worked really well and Rahul
you mentioned about like Leverage when
you're interviewing you have leverage
but also I've seen that you can also
have leverage within a company if you're
a really high performer your manager
wants to retain you so if you ask for
things and you've been doing a lot of
great work or you've been solving a lot
of their problems they you'll see that
they're a lot more receptive to helping
you with your career growth or getting
things done whereas if you're a less
High achieving person you might be lower
in their list of priorities so there's
also ways to have leverage within if you
get a lot of things done for them and
you're really critical piece of the team
but what is also true with that is like
your manager can't snap their fingers
most places and promote you there are
processes that they have to work through
there's other people making the decision
what is true is they do have control
over a lot of things and you can have
leverage with them to say I really need
projects that are like feeding the areas
that you say I'm missing towards
promotions if I can't get that on this
team let's just be honest about that and
let me find a different team where I can
or look outside that is real that is a
thing that they can really affect but
they can't just say oh you know what
you're saying promote you or leave yeah
I'll promote you today it's just not
real unless it's a really tiny company
or like you work for the CEO or
something so yeah like I know when I was
at Airbnb all promotions before the
staff promo
were like essentially controlled by the
manager if the manager thought you were
ready you could get promoted to mid
level or to senior but senior to staff
that and and any promotion after that
was promotion by committee and I was
always like I don't know about these
committees bro even at Amazon when there
wasn't like committees for promo it was
like skip level normally like senior
manager up through through senior but
then like director for principal keep
going up the management chain so it
didn't it still wasn't up to your
manager unless again you were a senior
engineer working for a director which
would be somewhat unusual like it
happened it wasn't just like your
manager even there where there wasn't
panels yeah yeah that's interesting that
you mentioned that Zach about lower
levels more in control for your manager
I definitely noticed that if you're
trying to get promoted from Junior to
midlevel even if a committee is making
the decision there's not a lot of
ambiguity in that promo what your
manager says is probably what's going to
happen it's really important that you
and your manager are aligned and then at
the highest levels yeah you're going to
need to get sign off from VPS and Edge
leads and your manager becomes more and
more of a messenger middleman for that
committee and that's why it's even more
important to say you want to get
promoted earlier because then they can
start trying to get that feedback from
the committee earlier and you can see
what the company's thinking if you're
looking at those really high levels okay
I have just one more question and then
hopefully we'll have time for a couple
from the audience or maybe from the four
of you if you want to bring up anything
but the okay the first question I asked
was about evaluating different projects
the second question is about evaluating
manager now I want to talk about
evaluating the team so the joke I make
to people is if you're at Apple right
Apple has tons and tons of products and
if you're working on garage band good
luck atting promoted it's never going to
happen at least not at the senior level
like no one cares about garage band but
if you work on the iPhone or if you work
on one the core properties of Apple the
likelihood is way way higher so that's
like my at least one heuristic to use to
evaluate what team is the better vehicle
to get you the promotion so that's maybe
the last question I want to ask is how
do you all think about organization or
team within the company to get a staff
level promotion sure yeah I I think that
what you're saying is definitely true
and you can make the best of where you
are or what teams you're looking at if
you're working on garage band and you
find that real-time audio response in
the operating system is insufficient and
you go to the team that owns that point
that out to them show them where in
their code or even ask if you can sit
with their team and fix that and then
you make that change or you affect that
change as a strong partner that is very
different than you made the sliders a
little bit smoother and garage band so
there are ways to leverage where you're
at to have higher impact in visibility
but certainly if you are on the flagship
product that visibility comes for free
for me the most important thing wasn't
necessarily the project that I was
working on being high impact it was if I
cared about the project I was working on
because that's when I can do my best
work so if I was working on challenging
problems that I found interesting I
would almost always flourish because I
could give my best and I could step up
to meet any Challenge and I felt
interested to dive in and get into the
week needs and really solve the problems
facing our users and if you also are a
user of the product and you're like
passionate about it depending on what it
is it's going to be so much easier for
you to give it your all to show up to be
a good Advocate to influence other
people it's hard to do that when you
don't give a [__] about what you're
doing so for me there was a time where I
was interviewing at Google and they were
like you do you want to work on ads I
don't give a [__] about that I'm not
going to lie I that wouldn't be exciting
to me I don't want to get up everyday
and work on ads for some people it would
be really fun because it's at a huge
scale it's at a really highly
influential part of Google's business
obviously for me I it could have been
the most influential project and if I
didn't care I wasn't going to be showing
up so that's how I've taken things in my
career is based on my own passion as
opposed to like the impact of the
business and then turned my passion into
something yeah so there's a few General
Trends I've noticed with promotions and
it just depends on the levels so for
typically up to senior there is scope
for promotion on pretty much any team
anywhere at least from what I've seen
within Fang if you're looking for
promotions past senior so L6 plus it
becomes a little more nuanced and I've
seen that there's generally certain
teams that uh can get promoted more
easily this all depends you know on
those particular team situation but one
cut that is interesting to think about
is product teams versus INF structure
teams past L5 so going into staff and
hire I've generally tended to see that
there's a lot more senior Engineers on
infrastructure teams and my thinking for
why that is the case is product
Engineers the way that you have huge
impact past L6 is typically through
leverage of controlling large projects
with many different Engineers on them
and there's a limited number of those
spots so if you want to be the one
building the overhaul of some major
product experience you want to be that
Tech lead one person for 60 Engineers so
there's a lot less spots for that
whereas on infrastructure teams people
who are building underlying pieces that
are very technically complicated and
they help everyone at the company move
faster there's natural leverage in the
technology itself and so there's a lot
more roles and opportunities I've seen
on infrastructure teams specifically for
these very tail more senior promos past
L6 and and onwards and I've definitely
experienced that I'm on an
infrastructure team and my team is quite
senior relative to other teams that I've
seen and I think it's just a natural
setup for how the ORS are set up and The
Leverage that you get from the
technology versus The Leverage of
leading a team yeah I want to follow up
there because I've actually been in both
positions there at Netflix I was more of
like a tech lead staff person on
infrastructure team building out like
that graph database and then at Airbnb I
was like the tech lead on pricing and
availability where I was more of a
product like Tech lead data engineer and
I've noticed especially in data
engineering that is even more the case
where it's like the more you lean into
more of like infrastructure and you're
not just like building like singular
pipelines but you're building like how
stuff is uh being done if you're
focusing more on the how work gets done
as opposed to what work gets done that
is definitely something I've noticed as
as get further along the ladder that you
need to have more of that because then
it's like if you are changing how other
Engineers are doing their job and like
you're saving Engineers five 10 minutes
a day but then that scales across
hundreds of Engineers you're saving so
much time and energy and creating so
much efficiency and that's a great way
to be leveraged and I that's why I think
I totally agree with Ryan's point on
there's a lot more opportunities in
infrastructure teams in big tech for
that because of you are impacting how
work is getting done as opposed to like
what work is getting done and that yeah
100% totally agree with that so I I will
frame it a little bit differently yes
that is true like infrastructure work
often Bridges a number of different
teams and has naturally a certain amount
of impact because it might be a
foundational piece of
infrastructure but I think that what you
need to see is what is the impact
available and do managers in that space
know how to promote people and then who
sees the work that you do on that team
if you're the senior most person on an
infrastructure team and you work on a
piece of infrastructure that no other
senior staff engineer sees it probably
isn't going to be a thing that can get
you promoted so when you're evaluating
it yes infrastructure teams tend to have
those like opportunities more frequently
but just because it's infrastructure
doesn't mean it's set up for that and
just because it's product work doesn't
mean it isn't you still have to do the
next level of evaluation of like what
work do I do there that is going to have
this impact okay so I want to go through
a bunch of the question there's a ton of
questions in the chat so for the last 10
minutes we can go through a couple of
those that I pulled out but before that
I'm curious Zach Lee Carly Ryan if you
have anything that you saw was
particularly interesting or anything
else that we haven't covered so far that
you want to talk about I'm cool to go to
audience Q&A let's see how many we can
bang out yeah so actually yeah for these
Maybe my my preference or my opinion
would be let's focus on throughput
rather than depth so maybe just one
maybe two of us can answer okay so the
first one here is highly voted how do
you compete with employees who are in
proximity to the manager versus those
who might be full-time remote or hybrid
and they don't have as much FaceTime or
interaction with the manager Al go big
thing there is just documentation
communication make sure that you have
proof right proof is going to be the big
thing of I would say that's going to be
the number one thing there and and I
haven't really worked on a hybrid
environment I've only really worked in a
full remote environment but I think
that's going to be your biggest way to
to get leverag here I like it was asking
about the appropriate number of hours so
I'm curious for each of you this some
meaningful project that you worked on to
get to staff do you feel like you had to
put in an abnormally higher number of
hours to get that promotion mine was
more than 40 hours a week I'll say that
yeah same same like for me I was
probably working like 50 55 and at
Netflix when I was building out that
graph database I was grinding for sure
yep yeah same I would say somewhere 50
to 60 always got my sleep but I was
working most of my week or most of all
of my weekdays that being said I've seen
people get promoted working 40 as well
but I was just down to grind so that's
what I did I guess as an outlier I don't
I did not when I got that promotion as a
manager work more than 40 hours a week I
had earlier in my career as an engineer
worked a lot more than that a lot of
that has to do with what you're doing
and where the time is going and it may
be the case that to deliver something it
is going to require more time if you're
working on something here's my
perspective I worked on Force multiply a
lot more than on individual delivery and
it's not to say other people were like
doing it wrong not at all but like the
people side can show that impact in less
hours spent so if you can make people
super super effective then your the
number of hours you work might not have
the same correlation to impact as when
you are delivering something yourself
that's super impactful that's it yeah I
guess if we're going around the circle
I'll say that yeah I the way I viewed it
is I never viewed it as okay this week
I'm working 50 hours I've never thought
of my work that way I've always started
with okay what do I want to get done
this week and yeah very frequently the
amount of time I would need to dedicate
to get that done would be more than 40
it' be like 60 but then the following it
could be like 30 so I I view my job less
as here's the number of hours I'm
working and much more about what is the
goal of what I'm trying to do rugu has a
highly voted question titles outside of
big Tech are generally inflated so you
might be a principal or senior principal
or distinguished engineer at a startup
but then you get down leveled when you
go into meta or Google what should these
people do in terms of in terms of work
or impact to avoid being down leveled
when they interview at fank getting
downlevel it's because you're not at the
level they expect you to be I don't
really it sucks but that's the truth you
can't avoid it unless you just are
better or interview better sounds me but
that's just the truth like a lot of
times they're inflated because they have
to do that like it Banks your vice
president at like mid-level engineering
sometimes it just happens so I wouldn't
focus on that I would focus on looking
at what those jobs mean at those
companies and like maybe you're working
as a principal engineer but that's
senior engineer work at these companies
or senior engineer scope at these
companies so you're not getting down
levels you're getting leveled
correctly those companies but you need
to know what is the right thing to
Target don't just Target L5 and you know
that are mid-level and hope that they
like see how brilliant you are and
instead give you an offer for a senior
but don't think that it's like a down
level because your title changed y
especially when you're taking the step
from these outside companies into big
tech companies if you're getting paid
three times as much and your title is
two steps lower what the [__] do you
care like you are getting paid just like
if you are doing meaningful work at the
level that you are capable of like the
title what it doesn't I yeah that's what
happened for me I know I was a mid-level
engineer at a startup and then when I
got the job at Facebook I got a junior
role at Facebook so I'm from mid-level
to Junior but it was like an 80% bump in
pay so I was like okay sure I'll go down
the ladder for 80% more money yeah I'm
down yeah and also about the yeah the
levels are arbitrary but if you see the
scope of what you're doing and you
compare that to the scope of what these
other companies expect at those levels
you can see there's some mapping of okay
I'm leading a small team and I'm called
a vice president maybe that's a senior
engineer at Fang and so you can think
more about the work itself rather than
just the titles all right what do you
all think do we have time for one more
before before we do like closing
remarks yeah let go for it let's go for
it all righten asked a long time ago um
seniority also open up more
opportunity like more ability to work on
interesting projects or with cool people
and so in that case it's a chicken and
egg problem right where you can't get
promoted until you have big enough
projects but you don't get big enough
projects until you get promoted so any
commentary on that yeah I would say that
to some extent yes it does help to have
seniority but I guess seniority doesn't
matter as much as your internal brand so
if you're someone who's known to get big
things done and your manager your
director or your senior manager they
have some big problem think about who
they're thinking to give that problem if
you're the first person that comes to
mind that's where you want to be and
your level often correlates so if you're
already already by senior person you're
probably getting things done and your
manager trusts you to solve that problem
so you are have more opportunities as a
result but also if you have great
visibility you're someone who is well
known internally and you're a rising
person that solves these big problems
you can still get those problems as well
so the commonality is being visible
being known as someone who can get
things done will give you more
opportunities I will say title is a way
to get doors to open it is not the only
way to get doors to open so it is very
similar to what Ryan said yes you might
be trusted with a larger project based
solely on title some places if you like
just got there and you're brand new but
you were hired into a role at a certain
level but you can be someone that you
know is a mid-level engineer but be
given really high scope because you have
a manager that has convinced people of
this your own actions have already
convinced people of and you have that
trust you have a sponsor that is a like
director level person that thinks you
should take something on like you
essentially you're going to have to find
that scope and get those doors to open
it's not just title title can help okay
beautiful so in case people might need
to drop off right at 11: California time
then I I thought we could maybe do
closing remarks I I might stick around
for a few minutes after and just help
out answer so if any of you four want to
stick around with me would love that but
before we go back to answering questions
why don't we go around just say hey like
maybe give them a pointer to where you
want people to follow you or any call to
action so Zach do you want to go first
yeah for surey hey everyone I teach a
lot of stuff about data engineering data
science all that stuff so if you go to
data expert.i you can make a free
account there there's a lot of free
stuff there and actually I just built
out a SQL leite code project so data
engineer. backquestions there's 50
questions there a lot of those SQL
questions are really hard and they're
free to try right now very difficult but
definitely I'd love feedback on all of
that I'll pass it to Ryan yeah you so
for where to find me you can find me on
LinkedIn I also write on substack if you
thought this content was interesting or
relevant to you that's basically
everything I write about I try to write
about career progression to staff
hopefully it's helpful for you and you
can just check LinkedIn and then most of
my stuff's there I second I second that
his is the developing Dev really good
it's really good like exactly I pass it
yeah so roll linked put our LinkedIn
links in there that's probably the best
starting point I also write on substack
because I write a lot of words I'm not
very concise so substack doesn't have
the same limits but I also do find that
it it is a better place to be able to
find things later and Link out and
whatever you can start at the LinkedIn
but substack I write about a lot of like
Tech Career things I also write about a
lot of mental health things I'm an
autistic person I have ADHD that makes
some things hard and some things easier
but like I I write a lot about keeping
your mental health up or mine not being
kept up and what I'm trying to do about
it and stuff like that as well yeah I'm
supposed to pass it off Carly I will say
Lee is awesome to follow for uh general
advice and just like awesome
vulnerability so I think that your
content's amazingly and I feel like Zach
really paved the way there on talking
about Mental Health on LinkedIn and got
so much flak for it on Reddit Jes like
you triggered those nerds LinkedIn
lunatic bro I also write a lot on
LinkedIn and on substack I [__] post a
lot on Instagram so if you guys are into
that I used to write a lot more about
career stuff but I think that people
like Ryan are taking the Baton from me
and doing a much better job and more
thoughtful job so I try to keep levity
on LinkedIn because I feel like it gets
too serious sometimes so if you like
jokes about Linux and other random stuff
that's where I've pivoted to so okay
amazing and then IO LinkedIn I
definitely post a as well similar to
everyone here and then the two things I
want to show are number one my YouTube
channel I that's why the platform I
spend the most time on and then the
second thing I want to just mention is
that later today we have an event which
is a case study of another person aside
from Ryan Ryan is probably the most
famous person who went from E3 to E6 in
three years we found someone else and
that person's giving a talk later today
so I wanted to put those two links in
the chat and and I care about this topic
a lot I actually teach a course
literally called senior to staff it's
not going on right now but at some point
I'll open it up again but yeah I just
feel like this is something I think
about a lot and I care about a lot so I
appreciate all of you attending and I
appreciate all four of the other
panelists to be very thoughtful and and
taking some time out of their day
whoever needs to drop I'm going to hang
out for a little bit too so we we'll see
what we can get through before everyone
gets tired of it and have meetings
manager life is meetings endless see
y'all later
y I have a meeting also but thanks
everyone hope you like the event thanks
for for
hosting got three of us for a little
while longer let's see what we so
there's one on here from Beast Mond
talking about visibility and promoting
yourself I will say this feels dirty
sometimes or it feels bad or you some
people are like more naturally shy or
they are a little more reserved how you
get that visibility can vary you have to
have it to move up period people have to
see people in positions that can speak
on your behalf have to know what you're
doing and support you but it doesn't
mean that you have to every time you do
an interesting thing post about it on a
message board or in slack or something
but it might be in the form of you do
Tech talks after a major is shipped or
you run the tech talk series and get
other people to be showing up so you're
doing that in a meta way it could be
that you everyone knows who you are
because you answer the questions on the
internal stack Overflow or whatever it
is there are lots of ways it does not
have something that you're uncomfortable
doing to like self-promote but you must
be visible yeah and I I think like
visibility as well is also from building
an internal brand is do your teammates
feel comfortable asking you questions
are you approachable are you someone who
like you can help unblock people because
like when you go to get promoted like
you have to have all that peer feedback
right so can you have three can you do
can you have at least three or four
co-workers who are like yeah this guy's
awesome and can you like and that they
can that you can actually they can
actually vouge for you that's if you can
cross disciplines with that it goes even
further if you can be a person that
product managers are like yeah they ask
the best questions and they get things
done cool if the data scientists are
like yeah they make sure to instrument
things so we can always figure out what
happened like the more people in
different places the better because if
you're just like oh Engineers love him
but product managers hate them you're
still not moving up okay so Ain asked
very early on and we just never got back
to it what is the main inflection point
for you when you decided to seek uh
promotion and then also was it the money
was it the title was it better work life
balance that you thought you might get
moving up so I will say for me I wanted
to do a certain kind of work and that
was something that I saw that people
with higher titles that people in senior
engineering roles principal engineering
roles at Amazon were getting to do that
I wanted to do and I did just start
doing them but it was also like one of
the main reasons I wanted to move up and
a lot of that work was like influencing
people on the management side that were
higher up like being able to get the
feel from other engineers and then
influence and make things better for
them it was mentoring people and being
able to do that effectively and
understand what it actually takes get
there and if I haven't done it myself
how am I going to tell them how to get
to senior if I can't get to senior or
whatever so that was the main thing for
me but yeah of course I like getting
paid like that's cool but it was a lot
about the kind of work I wanted to do
yeah two two things I want to call out
here one first of all Erin sorry I
missed it I'm glad you're still here so
two things that came to mind for me
about what I the reason I wanted staff
yeah first of all money is good money is
nice and the thing is that when you get
promoted in big Tech at least your
compensation doesn't go up linearly it
goes up
geometrically in the sense that you're
not it's not like you get paid
$220,000 uh from going to entry level to
mid level and then 20K more from mid
level to senior you probably get paid
like 50k more mid level to senior and
going from senior to staff you probably
get paid like 100 or 200k more right so
there's a substantial difference in the
amount of total compensation you receive
by getting to staff and I think money is
optionality and I like that and that
curve also changes based on the growth
of the company so so a lot of times your
mix of compensation moves more towards
stock when you are getting to these
higher levels and so yes it can be that
they're targeting to pay you 150k more
but then if the company's stock also
doubles now you're making like 600k more
having moved up and moved a lot of your
compensation towards rsus or other
stock-based comp so that's another thing
that like it opens up growth with the
company but that also comes with risk
because yeah want to add to that though
that does come with a lot of risk cuz I
actually had the opposite experience cuz
when I signed at Airbnb I got a stock my
grant was like 1.5 million over four
years and but that was at when the share
price was at 210 and then when I was
there in 6 months it went from 210 to 80
so my $1.5 million went to like 600k and
I'm like damn I'm like yeah I didn't
know I didn't know a man could lose so
much money in six months but and it just
varies while I was at Amazon I was there
from 2012 to 2021 or something in the
stock oh yeah that's up and to the right
that's just amazing but like at Google
like the stock is about back to where my
grant was I don't know it's not always
that I'm just saying that is a another
thing that changes yeah and well one
more thing I wanted to add and this
might sound maybe Politically Incorrect
or not so good to think about but
pedigree matters I I don't care how much
people talk about oh Tech ism is Merit
based pedigree and like name brand
matters a ton because I think
fundamentally humans are we we just do
pattern matching and in some ways that's
good in some ways it's bad right like it
could it could be held against you if
people have pattern matches on like race
or gender that's obviously bad but there
is also maybe the the flip side which is
hey you worked at meta or Google and
you're a staff engineer at Google most
of other staff engineers at Google are
pretty good and so from pattern matching
I assume you're pretty good and so I
really wanted to be able to effectively
set a floor on my next job or on my
startup to say hey I am an ex meta staff
engineer and you can call that ego you
can call that whatever you want but that
did matter to me and I think it should
matter to anyone who really thinks about
career progression and job hopping okay
I'm gonna answer one from Ram that just
whatever is easy to answer what is the
average team size for a staff engineer I
don't think about it as team size I
think about the number of people you
impact because you should be impacting
across teams unless you're like working
for a director then maybe you're
impacting the director's or or whatever
but I would say that like for a senior
engineer you should be at least
affecting like yourself and a senior
manager's scope so if you work for a
line manager but they report to a senior
manager hit that other senior manager's
teams too it's normally like 20 to 30
Engineers probably at staff it's
probably up to 50 to 60 or more more at
principal or the next step up it's
probably in the hundreds you're probably
affecting like a vp's org so that that
roughly if Zack or R you want to talk
something like when I was at Airbnb and
I was on like Marketplace because I was
on more like narrowly focusing on
pricing and availability but there's all
the other Marketplace Dynamic stuff and
that whole org was like 75 engineers and
I was impacting like the data in that
org but I was also not like the only
staff engineer I think there was like
five there's like Airbnb also leans very
heavy in the staff engineer if you look
at their job board right now they have
35 Staff positions open and that's it
that's that's it that's the only people
they're hiring right now it's just so
ridiculous like cool so the last one
maybe I saw and now it's so hard to
scroll in this chat oh my God I'm sorry
I don't know who it was but it was
asking about politics and how that
affects things and whatever
relationships matter people matter you
can call it politics if you want but
it's all people there are people that
are jerks and you have to play nice with
them to move up there are people that
are backstabbing and they are using
politics in the negative way to move up
you probably aren't going to change that
or get them fired or bring them down you
need to bring yourself up when you're
talking about politics what kind is it
if it's really toxic maybe it's just not
the right place but otherwise a lot of
times when people say politics what they
mean is I can't communicate very clearly
with people in executive roles or I
don't get along well with this other
team or whatever and you just have to
fix that you have to be able to do that
and you also whomever ask sorry asked
about NE
neurodiversity absolutely I am autistic
I have ADHD I have depression I have
anxiety it is hard I had to learn some
lessons in a hard way I ran in
eventually a manager was like Hey you
are right with almost everything that
you say but the way that you say it can
be too blunt and people can't hear it so
you need to find ways to be heard and be
right not just be right and so it was
like oh if you are just like no that
will never work people might not listen
to you but if you're like oh hey the
last system that I worked on we tried to
do it that way and it really fell apart
so have you considered like when you hit
this inflection point will your the
system still stand up that's a much
different way of saying it and people
are going to be much more receptive I
ask a lot of questions I make a lot
fewer state hey have you thought about
this hey what about that oh you know
what I don't know if that's going to
work did you prototype that asking those
things is much different than your idea
is terrible and it will never work even
if you know that to be true you need to
get it to be heard that's my general
take I think like one of the highest
measures of intelligence is not like
what you say it's what questions you ask
that's like a life thing too not just an
engineering thing yeah okay amazing for
the 130 of you who stuck around 10
minutes past the hour I really
appreciate it Lee Zach thanks so much
Zach I love the work you're doing in
data engineer and Lee I love the
consistency you have with writing so
appreciate all of you awesome bye
everyone see you all